<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6573 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6573.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7228 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7228.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7252 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7641 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7641.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8132 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8132.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-suit-architecture SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-suit-architecture.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-suit-information-model SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-suit-information-model.xml">
  <!ENTITY W3C.REC-html52-20171214 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-html52-20171214.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-hartke-t2trg-data-hub-03" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>Thing-to-Thing Data Hub</title>

    <author initials="K." surname="Hartke" fullname="Klaus Hartke">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Torshamnsgatan 23</street>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <code>SE-16483</code>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>klaus.hartke@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>Thing-to-Thing Research Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>
        The "Thing-to-Thing Data Hub" is a RESTful, hypermedia-driven Web
        application that can be used in Thing-to-Thing communications to share
        data items such as thing descriptions, configurations, resource
        descriptions, or firmware updates at a central location.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
        In Thing-to-Thing communication, there is often a need to share data
        items of common interest through a central location. For example, the
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory">Resource
        Directory</xref> aggregates descriptions of Web resources held on
        constrained nodes, which enables other nodes to easily discover these
        resources. Similarly, a <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-suit-architecture">Firmware Server</xref> stores stores
        firmware images and manifests, making this data available to deployed
        devices, commissioning tools, and other services.
      </t>

      <t>
        As more and more Thing-to-Thing applications are implemented, it becomes
        increasingly important being able to not only share resource
        descriptions and firmware updates but also many other kinds of data,
        such as default configurations for new devices, service locations, or
        certificate revocation lists. Resource directories and firmware servers
        are not a good fit for these kinds of data, as they're specialized to
        their use cases and generally not accepting any other kinds of data. And
        creating new, specialized applications for every type of data is not
        practical in the long term.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document defines a simple "data hub" application, a RESTful Web
        application with a machine-understandable hypermedia API. A "data hub"
        generalizes the concept of a central repository for different
        applications and is suitable for <xref target="RFC7228">constrained
        environments</xref>. Specifically, it enables clients to share data
        items in any format and provides means for creating, reading, observing,
        updating, deleting, and finding data items at a data hub server.
      </t>

      <t>
        Data hubs are intended to be used primarily with <xref
        target="RFC7252">Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP)</xref>.
        <vspace blankLines="10"/>
      </t>

      <t>
        Features:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            General
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The data hub generalizes the concept of a directory or repository to
            data items of any Internet media type. This means that applications
            using the data hub aren't stuck forever with the same media types or
            limited to just resource descriptions or firmware updates.
          </t>
          <t>
            Searchable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Clients can retrieve a subset of data items from a data hub based on
            item metadata.
          </t>
          <t>
            Observable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Data items published to a data hub are exposed as resources. As
            such, they can be <xref target="RFC7641">observed for changes</xref>
            over CoAP. This allows clients to stay informed of information that
            other clients update over time. As a result, the data hub functions
            similar to a <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub">Publish-Subscribe Broker</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Evolvable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The key differentiator of the data hub compared to <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory">Resource Directory</xref>
            and <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub">CoAP Publish-Subscribe
            Broker</xref> lies the evolvability of the application -- the ability to respond
            effectively to the need for changes without negatively impacting
            existing and new clients.<vspace blankLines="1"/>Data hubs enable
            fine-grained evolvability by driving all interactions by
            machine-understandable hypermedia elements. Features can be added,
            changed or removed in a safe, backwards-compatible way simply by
            updating the data hub representation to expose appropriate links and
            forms.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Notational Conventions">

        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          Terms defined in this document appear in <spanx>cursive</spanx> where
          they are introduced.
          <vspace blankLines="10"/>
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Data Model">

      <t>
        The data model of the "Thing-to-Thing Data Hub" application consists of
        three elements: the <spanx>data&nbsp;hub</spanx> itself, a
        <spanx>data&nbsp;collection</spanx>, and a number of
        <spanx>data&nbsp;items</spanx> that have been shared (<xref
        target="fig-data-hub"/>).
      </t>

<figure anchor="fig-data-hub" title="A Data Collection with a Number of Shared Data Items Hosted at a Data Hub"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     Data Hub
+-----------------------------------------------+
|                 ___                           |
|          Data  /   \                          |
|    Collection  \___/                          |
|                  |         ___                |
|                  |________/   \  Data Item    |
|                  |        \___/               |
|                  |         ___                |
|                  |________/   \  Data Item    |
|                  |        \___/               |
|                  |                   .        |
|                  |                   .        |
|                  |                   .        |
|                  |         ___                |
|                  |________/   \  Data Item    |
|                           \___/               |
|                                               |
+-----------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Data Hub">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A data hub is a Web application running on a Web server that hosts
            the data collection and the data items.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Data Collection">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A data collection is a collection resource that contains the data
            items.
          </t>
          <t>
            Representations of data collections MUST have the <xref
            target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">"application/coral+cbor"
            media type</xref>. The representations consist primarily of links to
            the data items. These links have the
            &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/item&gt; link relation
            type <xref target="RFC6573"/>. To reduce the
            number of round-trips, the representations MAY also embed (complete
            or partial) representations of the data items. Forms contained in
            the representation enable interactions with the data collection and
            the data items, as detailed in the following sections. The
            representations MAY additionally contain other links and forms that
            are not described in this document, such as a link with the
            &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/alternate&gt; link
            relation type <xref target="W3C.REC-html52-20171214"/> that
            references an alternate representation of the data
            collection resource.
          </t>
          <t>
            In this version of this document, a data hub is defined to have a
            depth of only one level. That is, all data item resources are
            organized directly under the top-level data collection resource.
            This could be extended to multiple levels in a future version.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Data Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A data item is a resource that is a member of the data collection
            resource.
          </t>
          <t>
            Data item representations can have any media type. However, a data
            collection MAY restrict the media types it accepts for publication.
            In this case, the form in the representation of the data collection
            for creating data items MUST list the acceptable media types using
            form fields of type &lt;http://coreapps.org/coap#accept&gt;.
          </t>
          <t>
            The representations of data items MAY link back to the data
            collection resource using the
            &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/collection&gt; link
            relation type <xref target="RFC6573"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Interaction Model">

      <t>
        The interaction model consists of eight potential interactions with a
        data hub: discovering and reading the data collection, and creating,
        reading, observing, updating, deleting, and finding shared data items in
        the data collection.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Discovering a Data Hub">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            In this version of this document, clients are assumed to be
            pre-configured with an entry-point IRI for a data collection at a data hub.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Reading a Collection">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A client can retrieve a representation of a data collection by
            dereferencing the entry-point IRI. As described above, the
            representation of the data collection includes links to (and,
            optionally, representations of) the data items in the data
            collection. The representation of the data collection also includes
            forms for creating, updating, deleting, and finding data items.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Creating an Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The representation of a data collection MAY contain a form with the
            &lt;http://coreapps.org/collections#create&gt; operation type. Submitting this form with a
            representation in one of the acceptable media types creates a new
            data item in the data collection. The acceptable media types are
            indicated by form fields of type &lt;http://coreapps.org/coap#accept&gt;.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations of this version of this document MUST use the method
            implied by the &lt;http://coreapps.org/collections#create&gt;
            operation type, i.e., the <xref target="RFC7252">POST method</xref>.
            A form indicating different a method MUST be ignored.
          </t>
          <t>
            On success,
            the location of the created data item MUST be conveyed in a 2.01
            (Created) response using the <xref target="RFC7252">Location-Path
            and Location-Query options</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Reading an Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A client can retrieve a representation of a data item by following a
            link with the &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/item&gt;
            link relation type in the representation of the data collection.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Observing an Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A client can observe a data item by following a link with the
            &lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/item&gt; link relation
            type in the representation of the data collection and observing the
            target resource as specified in <xref target="RFC7641">RFC
            7641</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Updating an Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            For each data item in a data collection, the representation of the
            data collection MAY include a form with the &lt;http://coreapps.org/base#update&gt;
            operation type nested within the link to the data item. Submitting
            this form updates the data item to the submitted representation.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations of this version of this document MUST use the method
            implied by the &lt;http://coreapps.org/base#update&gt; operation
            type, i.e., the <xref target="RFC7252">PUT method</xref>. A form
            indicating different a method MUST be ignored.
          </t>
          <t>
            On success, a 2.04 (Changed) response is returned.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Deleting an Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            For each data item in a data collection, the representation of the
            data collection MAY include a form with the &lt;http://coreapps.org/collections#delete&gt;
            operation type nested within the link to the data item. Submitting
            this form deletes the data item from the data collection.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations of this version of this document MUST use the method
            implied by the &lt;http://coreapps.org/collections#delete&gt;
            operation type, i.e., the <xref target="RFC7252">DELETE
            method</xref>. A form indicating different a method MUST be ignored.
          </t>
          <t>
            On success, a 2.02 (Deleted) response is returned.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Searching for Items">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The representation of a data collection MAY contain a form with the
            &lt;http://coreapps.org/base#search&gt; operation type. This form can be used to
            find data items in the data collection. Submitting this form with a
            search query returns the subset of data items that match the query.
          </t>
          <t>
            (TODO: Specify the representation format for search queries.)
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations of this version of this document MUST use the method
            implied by the &lt;http://coreapps.org/base#search&gt; operation
            type, i.e., the <xref target="RFC8132">FETCH method</xref>. A form
            indicating different a method MUST be ignored.
          </t>
          <t>
            On success, a 2.05 (Content) response is returned.
          </t>
          <t>
            (TODO: Specify the representation format for the response.)
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
        The data hub application relies on a Web transfer protocol like CoAP to
        exchange representations in a CoRAL serialization format. See Section 11
        of <xref target="RFC7252">RFC 7252</xref> and Section 7 of <xref
        target="RFC7641">RFC 7641</xref> for security considerations relating to
        CoAP. See Section 7 of <xref target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">RFC
        XXXX</xref> for security considerations relating to CoRAL.
      </t>

      <t>
        The data hub application does not define any specific mechanisms for
        protecting the confidentiality and integrity of messages exchanged
        between a data hub and a client. It is recommended that implementations
        employ application layer or transport layer mechanisms for interactions
        with a data hub.
      </t>

      <t>
        The data hub application does not define any specific mechanisms for
        protecting the confidentiality and integrity of representations of data
        items shared through a data hub. For scenarios where end-to-end security
        matters, such as for <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-suit-information-model">firmware updates</xref>,
        implementations should employ an object security mechanism.
      </t>

      <!--

      * authorization/access control
      * denial of service
      * ...

      -->

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
        This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2119;
      &RFC6573;
      &RFC7252;
      &RFC7641;
      &RFC8132;
      &I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC7228;

      &I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub;
      &I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory;
      &I-D.ietf-suit-architecture;
      &I-D.ietf-suit-information-model;

      &W3C.REC-html52-20171214;

    </references>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

      <!-- sorted by last name -->
      <t>
        Thanks to
        Christian Ams&uuml;ss and
        Jaime Jim&eacute;nez
        for helpful comments and discussions that have shaped the
        document.
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

  </back>

</rfc>
