<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5988 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.5988.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6573 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6573.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6690 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.6690.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7252 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7252.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC7641 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.7641.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.hartke-core-apps SYSTEM "reference.I-D.hartke-core-apps.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.hartke-core-lighting SYSTEM "reference.I-D.hartke-core-lighting.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral SYSTEM "reference.I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub SYSTEM "reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory SYSTEM "reference.I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.vial-core-mirror-server SYSTEM "reference.I-D.vial-core-mirror-server.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-hartke-t2trg-data-hub-01" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>Thing-to-Thing Data Hub</title>

    <author initials="K." surname="Hartke" fullname="Klaus Hartke">
      <organization>Universitaet Bremen TZI</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Postfach 330440</street>
          <city>Bremen</city>
          <code>D-28359</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+49-421-218-63905</phone>
        <email>hartke@tzi.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>Thing-to-Thing Research Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>
        A Thing-to-Thing Data Hub is a RESTful, hypermedia-driven Web
        application that can be used in Thing-to-Thing communication
        to<vspace/>share information such as thing descriptions, configurations,
        resource descriptions or firmware updates at a central location.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
        In Thing-to-Thing communication, there is often a need to share
        information of common interest at a central location. For example, a
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory">CoRE Resource
        Directory</xref> aggregates descriptions of resources held on other
        servers, which enables things to easily discover these resources.
        Similarly, a <xref target="WOT">W3C Web-of-Things Thing Description
        Repository</xref> stores the semantic metadata of things as well as
        functional descriptions of their interfaces, making this information
        available to Web dashboards, commissioning tools and other things.
      </t>

      <t>
        As more and more thing-to-thing applications are implemented, it becomes
        increasingly important to be able to share also other data than resource
        and thing descriptions, such as the sleep schedules of devices, default
        configurations for new devices, firmware updates, or certificate
        revocation lists. Resource directory and thing description repository
        are not always the best fit for this kind of data and defining a new
        specialized application for each use case is not practical in the long
        term.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document defines a simple "data hub" application, a RESTful Web
        application suitable for constrained environments that generalizes the
        concept of a central entity for sharing information. A data hub enables
        clients to share data items in any media type and provides means for
        creating, reading, observing, updating, deleting and finding shared
        items at a data hub server.
      </t>

      <t>
        The application is presented in the style of a <xref
        target="I-D.hartke-core-apps">CoRE Application Description</xref>. That
        is, the focus of the application interface is on the media types used by
        the data hub and all interactions are driven by links and forms.
      </t>

      <t>
        Features:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            General
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The generalization to any media type provides two advantages. The
            first is media type agility: applications using the data hub won't
            be stuck forever with the same media types. The second, as mentioned
            above, is that it may be useful to share also other information than
            resource and thing descriptions.
          </t>
          <t>
            Searchable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Submitting a search query allows clients to retrieve a subset of
            items from a data hub. Without this feature, a client would have to
            download and sort through the whole set of shared items. It is more
            efficient to filter the set at the data hub server. To make this
            work with any media type, a search request needs to specify both the
            media type of the desired items and a media type-specific search
            query.
          </t>
          <t>
            Observable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The items published to a data hub are exposed as resources and as
            such can be <xref target="RFC7641">observed for changes</xref>. This
            allows clients to stay informed of information that other clients
            update over a period of time. In effect, the data hub is similar in
            functioning to a <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub">CoAP
            Publish-Subscribe Broker</xref>, although this isn't the primary use
            case of a data hub.
          </t>
          <t>
            Evolvable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The key differentiator of the data hub compared to resource
            directory and publish-subscribe broker lies in the evolvability --
            the ability to respond effectively to change (such as the addition
            of new features) without negatively impacting both existing and new
            clients. The definition of the application interfaces purely in
            terms of standardized URI templates makes it very difficult to
            gradually evolve them; there are no versioning or capability
            negotiation mechanisms. The data hub facilitates fine-grained
            evolvability by driving all interactions by machine-understandable
            hypertext. Features can be added, changed or removed in a safe,
            backwards-compatible way simply by updating the data hub
            representation to expose matching links and forms.
          </t>
          <t>
            Customizable
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            TODO.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Terminology">

        <t>
          Readers are expected to be familiar with the terms and concepts
          described in <xref target="RFC5988"/>, <xref target="RFC6573"/>, and
          <xref target="I-D.hartke-core-apps"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Data Model">

      <t>
        The data model consists of four parts. The central part is the data
        hub, which has a number of shared items (<xref
        target="fig-data-hub"/>). A data hub can be queried with a search
        query, which yields a search result.
      </t>

<figure anchor="fig-data-hub" title="A Data Hub with a Number of Shared Items"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
      ___
Data /   \
 Hub \___/         ___
       |__________/   \ Item 1
       |   item   \___/
       |           ___
       |__________/   \ Item 2
       |   item   \___/
       |                  .
       |                  .
       |                  .
       |           ___
       |__________/   \ Item N
           item   \___/
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Data Hub">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A data hub resource is a collection of shared data items. Its
            representation primarily consists of links to the data item
            resources using the <xref target="RFC6573">"item" link relation
            type</xref>. To reduce the number of round-trips, it MAY also
            embed (complete or partial) representations of those item
            resources. Forms contained in the data hub representation enable
            interactions with the hub and items, as described in the following
            section. Additional links and forms not described here MAY be
            present (for example, a link with the "alternate" link relation
            type that references an alternate representation of the data hub
            resource).
          </t>
          <t>
            For a start, a data hub has only a depth of one level; i.e., all
            data item resources are organized directly under the top-level
            data hub resource. This could be extended to multiple levels in a
            future revision of this draft.
          </t>
          <t>
            Data hub representations are formatted in the <xref
            target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">"application/coral" media
            type</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A data hub item is a member of the collection.
          </t>
          <t>
            Item representations can in principle be formatted in any media
            type; a data hub deployment MAY restrict the media types it
            accepts for publication, though.
          </t>
          <t>
            The representations of items MAY link back to a data hub
            resource using the <xref target="RFC6573">"collection" link
            relation type</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Search Query">
            TODO.
          </t>
          <t>
            Search query representations are formatted in the <xref
            target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">"application/coral-query" media
            type</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Search Results">
            TODO.
          </t>
          <t>
            Search result representations are formatted in the <xref
            target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">"application/coral" media
            type</xref>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Interaction Model">

      <t>
        The interaction model consists of eight possible interactions with a
        data hub: discovering and reading the data hub, and creating, reading,
        observing, updating, deleting and finding shared items in the data
        hub.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Discovery">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            For a start, nodes are assumed to be pre-configured out-of-band
            with a link to a data hub.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Read Data Hub">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A node can retrieve a representation of the data hub by
            following the discovered link. The representation of the data
            hub includes links to (and/or literals with representations of)
            the items in the data hub. The data hub representation MAY also
            include forms for creating, updating, deleting and finding items.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Create Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The representation of a data hub MAY contain a form with the
            "create-item" form relation type. Submitting this form with a
            representation in one of the accepted content formats creates a
            new item in the data hub.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Read Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A node can retrieve a representation of an item by following one
            of the links with the "item" link relation type in the data hub
            representation.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Observe Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A node can observe an item by following one of the links with the
            "item" link relation type in the data hub representation and
            observing the target resource as specified in <xref
            target="RFC7641"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Update Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            For each item in a data hub, the representation of the
            data hub MAY indicate that the item is updatable. If an item
            is updatable, the link to the item includes the CoRAL Updatable
            Option, which defines a form with the "update" form relation type.
            Submitting this form updates the item in the data hub to the
            submitted representation.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Delete Item">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            For each item in a data hub, the representation of the
            data hub MAY indicate that the item is deletable. If an item
            is deletable, the link to the item includes the CoRAL Deletable
            Option, which defines a form with the "delete" form relation type.
            Submitting this form deletes the item from the data hub.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Find Items">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The representation of a data hub MAY contain a form with the
            "search" form relation type, which can be used to find items in
            the data hub. Submitting this form with a media type and a media
            type-specific filter query returns a subset of the data hub that
            matches the filter. (The details of this are TODO.)
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Application Description">

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Application name:">
            <vspace/>Thing-to-Thing Data Hub 1.0
          </t>
          <t hangText="URI schemes:">
            <vspace/><xref target="RFC7252">coap</xref>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Media types:">
            <vspace/><xref target="I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral">application/coral</xref>
            <!-- TODO: query -->
          </t>
          <t hangText="Link relation types:">
            <vspace/><xref target="RFC6573">collection</xref>
            <vspace/><xref target="RFC6573">item</xref>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Form relation types:">
            <vspace/><xref target="I-D.hartke-core-apps">create-item</xref>
            <vspace/><xref target="I-D.hartke-core-apps">update</xref>
            <vspace/><xref target="I-D.hartke-core-apps">delete</xref>
            <vspace/><xref target="I-D.hartke-core-apps">search</xref>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Form field names:">
            <vspace/>None.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Well-known locations:">
            <vspace/>None.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
            <vspace/>See <xref target="interoperability"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Security considerations:">
            <vspace/>See <xref target="security"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Contact:">
            <vspace/>See "Author's Address" section.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
            <vspace/>IESG
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Interoperability Considerations" anchor="interoperability">

      <t>
        TODO.
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

      <t>
        TODO.
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
        This document includes no request to IANA.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2119;
      &RFC6573;
      &RFC7252;
      &RFC7641;
      &I-D.hartke-core-apps;
      &I-D.hartke-t2trg-coral;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC5988;
      &RFC6690;
      &I-D.hartke-core-lighting;
      &I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub;
      &I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory;
      &I-D.vial-core-mirror-server;

      <reference anchor="WOT" target="http://w3c.github.io/wot/current-practices/wot-practices.html">
        <front>
          <title>WoT Current Practices</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Kovatsch" fullname="Matthias Kovatsch"/>
          <author initials="D." surname="Peintner" fullname="Daniel Peintner"/>
          <date month="November" day="11" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Related Work">

      <t>
        The data hub is an instance of the well-known collection pattern. As
        such, it might be used in places where a more specialized instance of
        the collection pattern is currently used, such as the bulletin board of
        <xref target="I-D.hartke-core-lighting">CoRE Lighting</xref>, the <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub">CoAP Publish-Subscribe Broker</xref>,
        or the <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory">CoRE Resource
        Directory</xref>. This section shows how these might be implemented
        using a data hub (without trying to replicate all of their features in
        detail).
      </t>

      <section title="CoRE Lighting">

        <t>
          <xref target="I-D.hartke-core-lighting">CoRE Lighting</xref> uses a
          JSON-based "bulletin board" to discover things such as light bulbs and
          light switches. Things are described by a thing description that
          contains both human-readable information and machine-understandable
          hypermedia controls which indicate the possible interactions with the
          thing.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-td" title="A Data Hub Storing Thing Descriptions"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+----------------------------------+
|   ___                            |
|  /   \ Data Hub                  |
|  \___/         ___               |
|    |__________/   \ Thing        |    +------------------------+
|    |   item   \___/ Description  |    |   ___                  |
|    |            |________________|____|__/   \ Light Bulb      |
|    |                     config  |    |  \___/ Configuration   |
|    |                             |    |                        |
|    |           ___               |    +------------------------+
|    |__________/   \ Thing        |    +------------------------+
|        item   \___/ Description  |    |   ___                  |
|                 |________________|____|__/   \ Light Remote    |
|                           about  |    |  \___/ Control State   |
|                                  |    |                        |
+----------------------------------+    +------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

        <t>
          <xref target="fig-td"/> shows a data hub with two thing
          descriptions, matching the example in Section 5.2.1 of <xref
          target="I-D.hartke-core-lighting"/>. The first thing description
          describes a light bulb and has a link with the "config" link relation
          type pointing to the configuration of the light bulb. The second thing
          description describes a light remote control (LRC) and has a link with
          the "about" link relation type pointing to the observable state of the
          LRC.
        </t>

        <t>
          Thing descriptions are represented in the
          "application/thing-description+json" media type (content format 65200
          in the example). A data hub representation thus could look as
          shown in <xref target="fig-lighting-example"/>.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-lighting-example" title="A Data Hub Representation With Two Thing Descriptions"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 ______________________________
|                              |
|  Form                        |
|   relation: 1 (create-item)  |
|   method: 2 (POST)           |
|   accept: 65200              |
|______________________________|
|                              |
|  Literal                     |
|   relation: 33 (item)        |
|   format: 65200              |
|   ________________________   |
|  |                        |  |
|  |  Thing Description 1   |  |
|  |________________________|  |
|______________________________|
|                              |
|  Literal                     |
|   relation: 33 (item)        |
|   format: 65200              |
|   ________________________   |
|  |                        |  |
|  |  Thing Description 2   |  |
|  |________________________|  |
|______________________________|
]]></artwork></figure>

      </section>

      <section title="CoAP Publish-Subscribe">

        <t>
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-pubsub">CoAP
          Publish-Subscribe</xref> provides means for sensor and actuator nodes
          with limited reachability to publish and receive data without having
          to be reachable at the same time. The basic operation involves clients
          called "publishers" updating "topic" resources at a server called the
          "broker", and clients called "subscribers" observing these resources
          (<xref target="fig-broker"/>).
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-broker" title="CoAP Publish-Subscribe"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 ____________            ____________            ____________
|            |--------->|            |          |            |
|  Publisher |<---------|   Broker   |          | Subscriber |
|  (Client)  |          |  (Server)  |<---------|  (Client)  |
|____________|          |____________|--------->|____________|
]]></artwork></figure>

        <t>
          A broker might be implemented as a data hub by creating the
          topics as resources on the data hub server and linking to these
          from the data hub resource with the "item" link relation type
          (<xref target="fig-pubsub"/>). Hypermedia controls in the data
          hub representation enable publishers to create, update and delete
          topics, and subscribers to read/observe these topics.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-pubsub" title="A Data Hub Acting as a Publish-Subscribe Broker"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+------------------------------+
|   ___                        |
|  /   \ Data Hub              |
|  \___/         ___           |
|    |__________/   \ Topic A  |
|    |   item   \___/          |
|    |           ___           |
|    |__________/   \ Topic B  |
|    |   item   \___/          |
|    |           ___           |
|    |__________/   \ Topic C  |
|        item   \___/          |
|                              |
+------------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

        <texttable anchor="mapping-pubsub" title="Mapping of Pub/Sub Interactions to Data Hub">
          <ttcol>Interaction</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Mapped to</ttcol>

          <c>DISCOVER</c>
          <c>Discovery /</c>
          <c></c>
          <c>Read Data Hub / </c>
          <c></c>
          <c>Find Items</c>

          <c>CREATE</c>
          <c>Create Item</c>

          <c>PUBLISH</c>
          <c>Update Item</c>

          <c>SUBSCRIBE</c>
          <c>Observe Item</c>

          <c>UNSUBSCRIBE</c>
          <c>Observe Item</c>

          <c>READ</c>
          <c>Read Item</c>

          <c>REMOVE</c>
          <c>Delete Item</c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section title="CoRE Resource Directory">

        <t>
          A <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory">CoRE Resource
          Directory</xref> hosts descriptions of resources held on other
          servers, allowing lookups to be performed for those descriptions. The
          descriptions are encoded as links in <xref target="RFC6690">CoRE Link
          Format</xref> that are annotated with a variety of link attributes
          providing the type of and hints about the linked resources.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-rd" title="A Data Hub Storing Links"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+----------------------------------+
|   ___                            |
|  /   \ Data Hub                  |
|  \___/         ___               |
|    |__________/   \ Link Format  |    +------------------------+
|    |    item  \___/ Resource     |    |   ___                  |
|    |            |________________|____|__/   \ Resource A      |
|    |                      hosts  |    |  \___/                 |
|    |                             |    |                        |
|    |           ___               |    +------------------------+
|    |__________/   \ Link Format  |    +------------------------+
|         item  \___/ Resource     |    |   ___                  |
|                 |________________|____|__/   \ Resource B      |
|                           hosts  |    |  \___/                 |
|                                  |    |                        |
+----------------------------------+    +------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

        <t>
          A data hub might store these resource descriptions such that
          each resource description becomes one item in the data hub and
          each item links to the respective resource (<xref target="fig-rd"/>).
        </t>

        <texttable anchor="mapping-rd" title="Mapping of Resource Directory Interactions to Data Hub">
          <ttcol>Interaction</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Mapped to</ttcol>

          <c>Discovery</c>
          <c>Discovery</c>

          <c>Registration</c>
          <c>Create Item</c>

          <c>Update</c>
          <c>Update Item</c>

          <c>Removal</c>
          <c>Delete Item</c>

          <c>Read Endpoint Links</c>
          <c>-</c>

          <c>Update Endpoint Links</c>
          <c>-</c>

          <c>Register a Group</c>
          <c>-</c>

          <c>Group Removal</c>
          <c>-</c>

          <c>Lookup</c>
          <c>Find Items</c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section title="CoRE Mirror Server">

        <t>
          Similar to a CoAP Publish-Subscribe Broker, a <xref
          target="I-D.vial-core-mirror-server">CoRE Mirror Server</xref> allows
          a sleepy device to store representations of their resources so that
          other devices can access the representations while it is sleeping.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig-mirror" title="A Data Hub Acting as a Mirror Server"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+----------------------------------+
|   ___                            |
|  /   \ Data Hub                  |
|  \___/          ___              |
|    |___________/   \ Mirrored    |
|    |    item   \___/ Resource A  |
|    |            ___              |
|    |___________/   \ Mirrored    |
|    |    item   \___/ Resource B  |
|    |            ___              |
|    |___________/   \ Mirrored    |
|         item   \___/ Resource C  |
|                                  |
+----------------------------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

        <texttable anchor="mapping-mirror" title="Mapping of Mirror Server Interactions to Data Hub">
          <ttcol>Interaction</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Mapped to</ttcol>

          <c>Discovery</c>
          <c>Discovery</c>

          <c>Registration</c>
          <c>Create Item</c>

          <c>Removal</c>
          <c>Delete Item</c>

          <c>Update Mirrored Resource</c>
          <c>Update Item</c>

          <c>Retrieve Mirrored Resource</c>
          <c>Read Item</c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

    <!--
    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">

      <t>
        Thanks to
        X,
        Y, and
        Z
        for helpful comments and discussions that have shaped the document.
      </t>

    </section>
    -->

    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->
    <!-- **************************************************************** -->

  </back>

</rfc>
